<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: windows | Carolyn Van Slyck]]></title>
  <link href="http://carolynvanslyck.com/blog/categories/windows/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://carolynvanslyck.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-16T15:13:13-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://carolynvanslyck.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Carolyn Van Slyck]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Install a Linux-like Environment on Your Windows Machine in Minutes]]></title>
    <link href="http://carolynvanslyck.com/blog/2016/01/stealth-lolnix/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://carolynvanslyck.com/blog/2016/01/stealth-lolnix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><figure style="text-align: center; float: right; margin: 5px">
  <img src="http://carolynvanslyck.com/images/stealth-lolnix/hipster-kitty.jpg" />
  <figcaption>Can haz lolnix?</figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>Sometimes it feels like Windows developers are left out of all the fun. The cool new tools and
technologies are all written by hipsters on their sexy Macs
with the intention of being deployed on unsexy Linux servers off in the cloud.
A decade ago, Windows developers didn&rsquo;t care. We had a very nice stack of Microsoft technology
and tools that just worked, and we weren&rsquo;t much interested in what the other team was up to.
At first it was just a trickle, tools from the other side, such as
git, snuck in. Then node and its front-end tools popped up,
and now everyone feels like they should really know what
Docker is all about. <em>Uh&hellip; whales, right?</em> <img src="http://carolynvanslyck.com/images/stealth-lolnix/docker.png" alt="docker docker docker mushroom!" class="emoji" /></p>

<p>The Windows, Linux and Mac OS X worlds are starting to collide and I am loving it!
My computing background is a total hodgepodge:
I wrote my first choose-your-own-adventure game with QBasic on DOS,
played Oregon Trail on my school&rsquo;s coveted Apple computer, administered linux web servers,
made a living slinging C# and now I get to spend my time helping to bring these worlds
closer together.</p>

<p>So back to the poor Windows developer, who can&rsquo;t seem to catch a break. Short of
buying expensive hardware or making the leap from Windows to a Linux desktop,
there weren&rsquo;t many ways to learn and try out some of these tools. While it
was always an option to totally geek out and setup Cygwin&hellip; let&rsquo;s be honest, that&rsquo;s
a daunting task that few were willing to sign up for.</p>

<p>Enter stage left: Git for Windows, my beloved Trojan Horse. Many Windows developers
have installed git, either manually or thanks to it being bundled with Visual Studio 2015.
But why did I call it a Trojan Horse? Because you don&rsquo;t just <em>get git</em> when you install it.
You also get a Linux-like environment that I lovingly call <strong>lolnix</strong>. After innocently running a simple installer,
not only do you have git, but you also have a new shell, bash, plus useful tools like
<code>curl</code>, <code>vim</code>, <code>cut</code>, <code>sed</code>, <code>grep</code>, and all sorts of goodies.</p>

<blockquote><p>lolnix = my pet name for a Mac OS X/Linux like environment on Windows</p></blockquote>

<p>This is nice but once I became used to having <em>some</em> of these tools
on my Windows machine, I wanted <em>all</em> of them. Recently I learned that I can go
even further with lolnix, with very little effort. Just switch
from installing <a href="https://git-for-windows.github.io/">Git for Windows</a> to <a href="http://git-for-windows.github.io/#download-sdk">Git for Windows SDK</a> and you now have access
to a cornucopia of tools because the SDK gives you <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Pacman#Installing_specific_packages">pacman</a>! No, not the hungry yellow
ghostbuster, but the package management tool. Armed with pacman, you can install
<a href="https://github.com/git-for-windows/MSYS2-packages">all sorts</a> of <a href="https://github.com/git-for-windows/MINGW-packages">fun tools</a>. Just one installer,
and you are up-and-running with a very functional Linux-like environment where
you can start playing with new tools at your leisure, no big bang required.</p>

<p>For me, I really wanted <code>make</code> on my Windows machine, as I&rsquo;m playing around
with some cross-platform Go development. {insert unrepentant pitch for the <a href="https://getcarina.com/docs/tutorials/docker-version-manager/">Docker Version Manager (dvm)</a> and
the <a href="https://getcarina.com/docs/getting-started/getting-started-carina-cli/">Carina CLI</a> here} So give it a shot and discover your own favorite tools today!</p>

<p><strong>A friendly note about command line terminals</strong></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know how to put this politely but the command-line experience on Windows sucks.
If you are using the default terminal in Windows, whether with CMD, PowerShell or Bash,
follow my tutorial <a href="/blog/2016/01/a-proper-windows-terminal/">Set Up a Proper Windows Terminal</a>.
I promise it is worth your time and you&rsquo;ll quickly see how much better things can be!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Set Up a Proper Windows Terminal]]></title>
    <link href="http://carolynvanslyck.com/blog/2016/01/a-proper-windows-terminal/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://carolynvanslyck.com/blog/2016/01/a-proper-windows-terminal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t know how to put this politely but the command-line experience on Windows sucks*.
If you are using the default terminal in Windows, whether with CMD, PowerShell or Bash,
you may not realize just how much better it could be. In this tutorial, you will setup
an alternative terminal that supports fun stuff: window resizing, tabs, intuitive copy/paste and pretty colors.</p>

<p><img src="/images/a-proper-windows-terminal/conemu-screenshot.png" alt="ConEmu Screenshot" /></p>

<p>* <span style="font-size: .8em">Yes, I am aware that the <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/Windows10GetsAFreshCommandPromptAndLotsOfHotkeys.aspx">terminal in Windows 10 has a lot of improvements</a>.
But I&rsquo;m still not using it because a) I&rsquo;m avoiding Windows 10 until I am forced to upgrade
and b) the alternative terminals are still nicer, with more features.</span></p>

<p>Before we start, let&rsquo;s get some definitions out of the way: the term <em>shell</em> refers to a
command-line interpreter that executes text commands (such as CMD, PowerShell or Bash) and <em>terminal</em> is the
graphical window that hosts a shell.</p>

<p>For years I have used ConsoleZ, and it is still something that I would recommend
as I find it to be one of the easiest terminals to configure. However, today
I want to demonstrate how to setup ConEmu. It supports all the same features as
ConsoleZ and while it may be a bit more complex to setup, it is also much more powerful
and <a href="http://conemu.github.io/en/TableOfContents.html">documented to boot</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li>Install ConEmu

<ul>
<li>If you have <a href="http://chocolatey.org">Chocolatey</a>, run <code>choco install conemu</code>.</li>
<li>Otherwise <a href="https://github.com/Maximus5/ConEmu/releases">download the installer</a> and run it, accepting all defaults.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Run ConEmu by selecting &ldquo;ConEmu&rdquo; from the Start Menu.</li>
</ol>


<p>Congratulations, you now have a civilized terminal installed and ready to use!
You could just stop right here and call it a day. I wouldn&rsquo;t blame you. Take it for
a spin and you&rsquo;ll see that you can resize the window, select text with your mouse to
copy it, and <code>CTRL+V</code> will paste. Huzzah!</p>

<p>However, a little bit of configuration is worth the effort. Below are some tweaks
that I find useful:</p>

<h2>Initial Configuration</h2>

<p>When you first start ConEmu, an <a href="http://conemu.github.io/en/SettingsFast.html">initial configuration prompt</a> is displayed.
It is safe to accept the defaults, but here are a few suggested changes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Select a default shell, e.g. CMD, Bash or PowerShell.</li>
<li>Choose a color scheme, my favorite is <a href="/images/a-proper-windows-terminal/monokai.png">Monokai</a>.</li>
<li>Opt-in to automatic updates for stable releases.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/a-proper-windows-terminal/fast-setup.png" alt="Fast Configuration Screenshot" /></p>

<h2>Replace Default Terminal</h2>

<p>This is ConEmu&rsquo;s killer feature. It is so frustrating to setup a terminal
just the way you like it, then be sent back to the dark ages when another process
pops up a terminal.</p>

<ol>
<li>Open ConEmu.</li>
<li>Go to <code>Settings &gt; Integration &gt; Default term</code>.</li>
<li>Check &ldquo;Force ConEmu as default terminal&rdquo; and &ldquo;Register on OS Startup&rdquo;.</li>
</ol>


<p>Voilà! Now when Visual Studio pops open a terminal, you are rewarded
with ConEmu, instead of the stinky old Windows command prompt.</p>

<h2>Tweaking Paste</h2>

<p>The default keybindings for paste are interesting but not what I expected out of the box.
<code>CTRL+V</code> will only paste the first line in your clipboard. <code>SHIFT+INS</code> will paste
the entire contents of your clipboard (including newlines). It also prompts you
if pasting new lines.</p>

<p>I prefer that <code>CTRL+V</code> pastes everything and doesn&rsquo;t give me any guff about it.
See the screenshot below for where to find the hotkeys.</p>

<ul>
<li>Map <code>CTRL+V</code> to paste everything. <code>Settings &gt; Keys and Macro &gt; User CTRL+V</code></li>
<li>Unmap paste first line. <code>Settings &gt; Keys and Macro &gt; User SHIFT+INS</code></li>
<li>Disable the newline warning. <code>Settings &gt; Keys and Macro &gt; Paste &gt; Confirm &lt;ENTER&gt; keypress</code></li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/a-proper-windows-terminal/paste-hotkey.png" alt="Remap Paste Hotkey" /></p>

<h2>Other Shells</h2>

<p>By default ConEmu starts up with the CMD shell. Once it is open, you could type
<code>powersehll</code>, <code>python</code> or <code>bash.exe --login</code> to use another shell.
However there is an easier way: <a href="http://conemu.github.io/en/Tasks.html">Tasks</a>. Tasks are quite powerful. Not only
can they start up new tabs with a different shell, but they can be used to run
saved commands in the current session.</p>

<p><img src="/images/a-proper-windows-terminal/run-task.png" alt="Run Task Menu" /></p>

<p>ConEmu comes with some predefined tasks, like starting an Administrator PowerShell session.
It can even detect your own setup and suggest some additional tasks. Since <a href="/blog/2016/01/stealth-lolnix/">I have have lolnix</a>, it automatically added a task to start up Bash for me.
To detect and add additional tasks, go to <code>Settings &gt; Startup &gt; Tasks</code> and click the &ldquo;Add default tasks&hellip;&rdquo; button.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://conemu.github.io/en/Tasks.html#create-new-task">tutorial for adding a new task</a> walks you through adding a task to start the Visual Studio Command Prompt,
which I find very useful.</p>

<h2>Making things pretty</h2>

<p>This is purely aesthetics. Here is what you need to change if you want to match
my screenshots:</p>

<ul>
<li>Use the monokai scheme. <code>Settings &gt; Features &gt; Colors &gt; Scheme</code></li>
<li>Use the consolas font, size 16 pt. <code>Settings &gt; Main</code></li>
<li>Hide the search bar. <code>Settings &gt; Appearance &gt; Show search field in tab bar</code></li>
<li>Hide the status bar. <code>Settings &gt; Features &gt; Status bar &gt; Show the status bar</code></li>
</ul>


<h1>Next Steps</h1>

<p>Congratulations, you are now more productive with the command line than 99% of
your Windows brethren. But don&rsquo;t stop now, there&rsquo;s more fun stuff you can do
now that you have a proper terminal:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/blog/2016/01/stealth-lolnix/">Install a Linux-like Environment on Your Windows Machine in Minutes</a></li>
<li>Save Keystrokes by Customizing your Bash Configuration <em>coming soon!</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
